Okay, so on this video then, we are going
to discuss two very important aspects of
project management, two very important
terms, enterprise environmental factor,
or EFs, an organizational process asset,
also known as OPA, right?
So we're going to discuss what they are
and what the difference is between them is
very important for you to understand that
for the PMP exam.
Now, both EF and OPA determine how work
gets done in an organisation, right?
How decisions are made,
how quickly decisions
are made, what procedures are used, right?
Both EF and OPA determine that.
But the look at them in slightly different
ways.
So I'm going to talk about enterprise
environmental factor first, Eve first.
Now, I always like to break up EF into a
couple of different categories,
internal factors and external.
factors, right?
So let's talk about the internal factors.
So these are factors within your
organization and you have no control over.
The project manager, you have no control
over it, right?
But it impacts your organisation.
Nonetheless, it impacts
your project, impacts
how the work gets done in your project.
So, for example, culture, organization
culture.
Any intangible factor like that,
right, culture of your organization,
risk tolerance.
I mean, what's an intangible factor.
It's not something you can touch or feel.
It is what it is.
And there's nothing really that you can do
anything about.
So organization's culture, right?
So that can determine how work gets done,
what procedures are being followed,
how quickly decisions are made,
right?
So imagine, for example, a hedge fund.
We always think of a hedge fund as being
fast pace, high stress, right?
They'll look at a number and immediately
have to make a decision.
So in an organization like that,
it's always quick, quick, quick,
quick, we have to make quick decisions.
Whereas in other organisations,
decisions might be a bit more laid back
just because of the culture of the
organisation.
And so that's going to have a direct
impact on your project.
Also, things like systems, any kind of
system, whether it's a manual system or an
automated system, that's
going to impact how work
gets done in your organisation
or how work gets done.
done on your project.
So let's think of
something very simple, not
even anything
project-related or work-related.
Let's think of something
simple like, you know,
here in the US we have
to prepare our taxes, right?
Not in a normal year, April 15th is our
tax deadline.
So how do we prepare our taxes?
Well, there's many different ways.
We could do it manually, right?
We could print out the tax forms, right,
or go to the post office and pick them up.
and write everything in, mail it in,
do everything manually.
That's one way.
Or we could buy a software tool,
there's several software tools available,
you can just go out and buy, or there's
many resources online that you could use.
Now, the end result might be the same,
but how you actually get there might be
different based on what system you're
using, whether you're using, whether
you're doing it manually, or which
software tool you use.
you're using, right?
The actual procedures might be different,
not might.
I mean, in this case, it will be
different.
So any kind of system is going to impact
how work gets done in your organization,
or how quickly work gets done in your
organization.
So whether it's a manual system or
not-mated system, any kind of system,
any kind of software tool will determine
how work gets done in your organization.
Now, one of the important tools,
right, for project management.
And, you know, one of the tools that's
discussed as part of the PMP exam is this
one called the PMIS, project management
information system.
And that is a tool or tools that you use
to manage your project.
So think of all the different software
tools that you use to manage your project.
So you might be using like Microsoft
Project, you might be using Microsoft
Office, you might be using
SharePoint, you might be
using Jira, there's all
these other primavera, right?
I mean, I've just named a few here.
I'm not endorsing any of them,
right?
But these are just some common tools that
I use.
Think of all the other different software
tools that you use.
So also including then your email system,
your file reporting system, you have a
business intelligence tool, you've got
your tracking system and archiving system
and so and so forth, configuration system
and change control system.
all of these collectively
make up the PMIS,
the project management information system.
So if it's a system,
anything that's a system
is an EF, an enterprise
environmental factor.
And then also then
other internal resources,
other internal organizational resources.
Again, that's going to impact a decision
making on your project.
It's going to impact your organization,
it's going to impact your project,
such as resources, availability of
resources, what their capabilities are,
materials, equipment, again, availability
of them.
Again, that's going to impact
decision-making on your project.
So these are some of the internal factors.
And again, regardless,
and EF is always, it's going to
impact your organisation or
impact your project in some way.
Now, let's talk about some of the external
factors.
So these are factors outside of the
project, outside of the organisation,
and it's going to impact your organisation
nonetheless.
And it's going to impact your organisation
impact your project nonetheless.
And again, your organization, in this
case, has no control, such as industry
standards, government regulations,
market conditions, political climate.
So as a simple example, with market
conditions, you have an abundance of labor
or you have a shortage
of labor, that's going
to impact decision-making
in your organization.
That's going to impact decision-making on
your project.
It's going to have a direct impact on your
project.
You have no control over that,
right?
Or industry standards, government
regulations, right?
Your ISO compliant, you have to follow ISO
standards.
Again, you don't have control over that,
right?
Or you're building a house.
You have to follow the building codes.
You can't decide, well, I don't want to
follow these building codes.
No, for your building house, you have to
follow those building codes, right?
That's impacted your organization.
That's impacted your project.
And again, you have no control.
control over that.
So these are all external factors.
Sometimes your competitors can be what
would be an EF.
Your competitor has marketed a product
that's superior to yours.
Or you have an increasing competition all
of a sudden.
That's impacted your organization.
You have no control over that.
In fact, a perfect example of an EF,
an external factor, which would be an EF,
would be the COVID situation.
This whole COVID situation that that
started in 2020.
It basically impacted the entire world.
Impacted every single organization
worldwide.
We didn't have any control over it.
No one had any control over it.
But that impacted every organization
worldwide.
So that would be a perfect example of an
EF.
Now, if you think of EF in these
categories, then, you know, that should
count for a good 9 to 95% of all EFs that
you'll come across on the exam.
As a general rule, an
EF is not a document,
as a general rule, but
there are exceptions.
I'll talk about the exceptions in just a
second.
Let's talk about the other term,
though, OPA, organizational process asset.
Because generally, organizational process
asset, best way to think of them are
documents, physical documentation
belonging to the organization,
such as policies and procedures.
So I like to break them up into these two
categories.
Policies and procedures and
knowledge-based.
So policies and procedures and processes.
So company policies,
when we're talking about
policies, I mean organizational policies.
Remember, these are organizational process
asset.
So company policies or policies for your
organization.
So that policy could be for your
department.
It could be for your entire organization
or it could be just for a team.
So policies, procedures.
templates, work instructions, right?
Company standards.
So again, all within the organization.
These are organizations documents.
And then knowledge base.
Knowledge base meaning then historical
information, right?
Lessons learned, historical lessons
learned, right?
Plus historical project files.
These would all be considered an op-op.
Now, something that you need to get your
head around here.
When I say project files, right,
when I say historical project files,
that's literally what I mean, historical
project files, not current project files.
Generally speaking, current project files
are not considered an OPA just yet.
Once the project is complete and now the
archive, now the historical information,
then they are now an OPA.
Current project files, these are project
files that are currently being worked on,
right?
The living breathing documents,
they are known as artifacts.
They can be updated at any time.
They are known as artifacts.
Once the project is complete and now those
artifacts become historical information,
now they are known as an opal,
right?
So, documentation such as, like said,
policies and procedures, templates,
work instructions, and then plus
historical information, historical
knowledge, historical knowledge base,
historical project files, lessons learnt,
plus things like preferred vendors list,
right?
These would be considered an OPA,
an organisational process asset.
Now, what about, say, external documents
such as government standards and industry
or government regulations and industry
standards, right?
Those are documents, what would they be
considered as?
Well, they would not be
considered an OPA because
OPA is specifically for your organization.
If they're external documents,
they would be considered an EF.
So this is the exception then that I was
saying.
Remember, as a general rule,
an EF is not a document, but there
are some situations where
documents could be considered an EF.
Here is an example.
and any external document.
So remember I mentioned, right, industry
standard government regulations, right?
Those are EF, they're external to your
organisation.
But the standards and regulations are
documented.
And so those documents would be considered
an EF.
So any external document
that's impacting your organisation
or impacting your project
would be considered an EF.
All right.
So make sure you understand then the
difference between EF and OPA.
It's very important to be able to
distinguish between the two, right?
Two very important factors that impact
your project.